Hello Friends.  Friends,
नमस्कार दोस्तों। दोस्तों ईरान इजराइल वॉर
what is the current situation regarding Iran Israel war?  Right now no
को लेकर अभी करंट सिचुएशन क्या है? अभी
one is able to understand anything because on one
किसी को कुछ समझ नहीं आ रहा क्योंकि एक
hand Donald Trump is claiming that a
तरफ डोन्ड ट्रंप यह क्लेम कर रहे हैं कि
complete ceasefire has been imposed.  On the other
पूरी तरह से सीज फायर हो चुका है। दूसरी
hand, no confirmation is coming from Iran.
तरफ ईरान की तरफ से कोई कंफर्मेशन नहीं आ
No concrete confirmation is coming.   On
रहा है। पुख्ता कंफर्मेशन नहीं आ रहा है।
one hand, Iran was indicating
ईरान एक तरफ इंडिकेट कर रहा था स्टार्टिंग
in the beginning that there was no ceasefire.  We are not going to bow down.
में कि कोई सीज फायर नहीं है। हम झुकने
But on the other hand, some such
वाले नहीं है। लेकिन दूसरी तरफ कुछ ऐसे
tweets have come through which this is being indicated.
ट्वीट्स आए जिसके माध्यम से ऐसा इंडिकेट
Look, it is still not confirmed
हो रहा है। देखिए अभी भी कंफर्म नहीं किया
but it is being indicated that Iran
गया लेकिन इंडिकेट हो रहा है कि ईरान भी
probably also wants ceasefire.  But just
शायद सीज फायर चाहता है। लेकिन अभी जस्ट
a while ago, just before I was recording the video, a
कुछ देर पहले जब मैं वीडियो रिकॉर्ड कर ही
notification came that there had been a
नोटिफिकेशन आता है कि इजराइल में वापस से
missile attack on Israel again.  So can there be
मिसाइल अटैक किया गया है। तो क्या इन सारे
some kind of ceasefire in all these situations
सिचुएशन में किसी प्रकार का सीज फायर हो
?  You can see this news, complete
सकता है? ये आप देख सकते हो खबर कंप्लीट
and total cease fire.  Trump announces end of
एंड टोटल सीज फायर। ट्रंप अनाउंससेस एंड
Israel Iran conflict and at the same time
ऑफ इजराइल ईरान कॉन्फ्लिक्ट और साथ ही साथ
Trump also said that this entire 12 day
ट्रंप ने यह भी कहा कि ये जो 12 दिन का
war would have continued for many years if
पूरा युद्ध था यह कई वर्षों तक चलता अगर
I had not stopped it.  So again here
मैं इसको नहीं रोकता। तो अगेन यहां पर जो
Donald Trump is trying to show himself that
डोनाल्ड ट्रंप हैं वो अपने आप को दिखाने
look I
की कोशिश कर रहे हैं कि देखो मैं चैंपियन
am the champion of ceasefire and I get the ceasefire done here.
हूं सीज फायर का और मैं यहां पर सीज फायर
So, let us understand this in a little detail as to
कराता हूं। तो इसको थोड़ा सा डिटेल में
what exactly
समझेंगे कि एग्जैक्टली क्या-क्या
developments are taking place.  Who is saying what
डेवलपमेंट्स हो रही हैं। कौन क्या कह रहा
?  We will know everything that has been said from Iran's side.
है? ईरान की तरफ से क्या कहा गया है वो सब
Let's get started.  Look,
कुछ जानेंगे। चलिए शुरुआत करते हैं। देखिए
first of all you all know that for the last 12
सबसे पहले तो आप सब जान रहे हैं पिछले 12
days there was a continuous war going on between Iran and
दिनों से लगातार वॉर चल रहा था ईरान और
Israel.  Here,
इजराइल के बीच में। यहां पर ईरान की तरफ
many dangerous missiles, hypersonic
से कई जो भयानक मिसाइल्स हैं, हाइपरसोनिक
missiles, different types of missiles
मिसाइल, अलग-अलग प्रकार के जो मिसाइल्स
, drones were being fired by Iran
हैं, ड्रोंस हैं वो दागे जा रहे थे इजराइल
on Israel and Israel was also attacking in the same manner with great enthusiasm.
के ऊपर और इजराइल भी उसी प्रकार से
But the turning
बढ़-चढ़कर हमला कर रहा था। लेकिन टर्निंग
point came when, as you all know,
पॉइंट तब आता है आप सब जानते हैं जो
America attacked the three
अमेरिका है उन्होंने ईरान के जो तीन
nuclear facilities of Iran, which you can see here,
न्यूक्लियर फैसिलिटीज आप देख रहे हो यहां
through B2 bombers.
पर बी टू बॉम्बर्स के माध्यम से उस पर
Specially for the
अटैक कर दिया। स्पेशली जो फॉर द वाला
facility, because the
फैसिलिटी है क्योंकि यहीं पर काफी नीचे
entire site has been built here, going very deep down, and
जाकर जो पूरा साइट है वो बनाया गया है और
destroying it was not easy, but
इसको खत्म करना आसान नहीं था लेकिन
America's claim is, you should understand carefully that there is
अमेरिका का क्लेम है आप ध्यान से समझिएगा
still no confirmation
अभी भी कंफर्मेशन नहीं है कि जो फदो का
whether the Fado nuclear site has actually been
न्यूक्लियर साइट है क्या एक्चुअल में वो
damaged, because superficially it can be seen
डैमेज हुआ है क्योंकि ऊपरी तौर पर दिख रहा
that yes, the B2 bomb that was
है कि हां यहां पर जो बी टू बॉम्ब से बम
thrown here, GBU 57, did penetrate,
फेंका गया था जीबीयू 57 तो वो पेनिट्रेट
but how exactly it would have
तो किया है लेकिन एग्जैक्टली अंदर कितना
gone inside and how much damage would have been caused, will be
गया होगा और कितना नुकसान पहुंचाया गया
known later, so
होगा वो आगे चलकर पता चलेगा तो अल्टीमेट
what is the ultimate that this red line is crossed.
क्या होता है कि यह रेड लाइन क्रॉस हो
Iran said that because of the
जाता है। ईरान का कहना था कि अमेरिका ने
way America bombed, we are
जिस तरह से बॉम्बिंग की अब हम यहां पर
not going to stop here.  Punishment will be given for this.
नहीं रुकने वाले। इसका पनिशमेंट दिया
And that is why if you see, late last
जाएगा। और इसीलिए अगर आप देखोगे तो कल देर
night suddenly the news came that Iran had
रात को अचानक से खबर आती है कि ईरान ने
attacked the US air bases.
यूएस के जो एयर बेसेस हैं उसके ऊपर हमला
Now the thing to understand is that if you
कर दिया। अब समझने की बात यह है कि अगर आप
see, Iran does not have the
देखोगे तो ईरान जो है उस उसके पास वो
missile technology that
मिसाइल की टेक्नोलॉजी नहीं है कि वो
can drop it on American land.  So it is
अमेरिका के लैंड पर जाकर गिरा सके। तो
obvious that he could have attacked the US assets across the
ऑब्वियस सी बात है यूएस के जो एसेट्स हैं
Middle East.
इस पूरे मिडिल ईस्ट के अंदर उसी के ऊपर वो
Now, if you look
अटैक कर सकता था। अब अगर आप देखेंगे इस
at this map, all the dots that you can
मैप के अंदर तो ये जितने भी डॉट्स आपको
see are the bases of the US
देखने को मिल रहे हैं ये यूएस के बेससेस
in the Middle East. And especially these red
हैं मिडिल ईस्ट में और स्पेशली ये जो रेड
dots that you can see,
वाला डॉट्स आप देख रहे हो ना ये एक प्रकार
you can call them permanent bases because the
से परमानेंट बेस आप कह सकते हैं क्योंकि
US has been working here for the last 15 years.
पिछले 15 वर्षों से यूएस के द्वारा यहां
In You In These
पर काम किया जा रहा था। इन यू इन इन
Bases was being worked on.  So
बेससेस के ऊपर काम किया जा रहा था। तो
what did Iran do suddenly? If you see
ईरान ने क्या किया अचानक से अगर आप देखोगे
last night, they attacked Qatar.  A
कल रात को तो ये जो क़तर है वहां पर हमला
barrage of missiles was launched.
कर दिया। मिसाइल्स की बौछार कर दिया।
What did the shower say that it is very
बौछार भी क्या यूएस का कहना था कि बहुत ही
weak, I will tell you about that later.  But
कमजोर है वो मैं आपको आगे बताऊंगा। लेकिन
again you can see that here in the Persian Gulf,
अगेन आप देख सकते हो यहां पर पर्शियन गल्फ
in Qatar, just near Doha,
में ये जो क़तर है दोहा के जस्ट पास में
there is an air base called Al
ही यहां पर एयर बेस है जिसका नाम है अल
Udeid Air Base and it is being said
उदैद एयरबेस और वहीं पर बताया जा रहा है
that the attack was carried out by Iran.  Now
कि हमला किया गया ईरान के द्वारा। अब हमले
what happened in the attack was that there were no casualties.
में भी क्या था ना कि कोई कैजुअलिटी नहीं
Because it is being said that Qatar was
हुई है। क्योंकि यह बोला जा रहा है कि कतर
already informed.
को पहले ही इन्फॉर्म कर दिया गया था।
Because Iran says, look, we have
क्योंकि ईरान का कहना है कि देखिए हमारा
no enmity with Qatar.  But
कतर से दुश्मनी नहीं है। लेकिन क़तर के
we want to attack the US airbase inside Qatar.
अंदर जो यूएस का एयरबेस है हम उसके ऊपर
So perhaps Iran had
अटैक करना चाहते हैं। तो शायद ईरान ने
already informed Qatar that we were
पहले ही इन्फॉर्म कर दिया था कतर को कि हम
launching missiles.  Whatever things
मिसाइल्स लॉन्च कर रहे हैं। जो भी चीजें
you evacuate, it is obvious that if you
आप खाली कर दो तो ऑब्वियस सी बात है जब आप
launch the missile after informing in advance then there are
पहले से बताकर करोगे मिसाइल लॉन्च तो कोई
less chances of any damage occurring.  So
नुकसान होने के कम चांसेस होते हैं। तो
if you see here, Iran says used the
यहां पर अगर आप देखोगे तो ईरान सेज यूज्ड
same number of bombs as the US.  Meaning that as much as
सेम नंबर ऑफ बॉम्ब्स एज यूएस। मतलब जितना
America used bombs
अमेरिका ने बॉम्ब का इस्तेमाल किया था
inside Iran,
ईरान के अंदर सेम उतना ही बॉम्ब का
Iran too has used the same number of bombs on US assets.
इस्तेमाल ईरान ने भी किया है यूएस एसेट के
So if you look here, as soon as
ऊपर। तो यहां पर अगर आप देखिए तो जैसे ही
this news comes, if you look at all the airspaces last night of
ये खबर आती है कल रात को जितने भी एयर
Kuwait, Bahrain, Qatar, UAE,
स्पेस थे कुवैत, बहरेन, क़तर, यूएई ये अगर
you will see flights all around it.
आप देखेंगे तो इसके आसपास चारों तरफ आपको
But
फ्लाइट्स नजर आ रहे होंगे। लेकिन पूरे
here in the entire Middle East, no
मिडिल ईस्ट में यहां पर जो है कोई भी
flights were flying.  Because it is
फ्लाइट उड़ान नहीं भर रही थी। क्योंकि
obvious that there would have been danger and last night it was
ऑब्वियस सी बात है खतरा हो जाता और कल रात
not even understandable
को तो समझ में भी नहीं आ रहा था कि यह
how much it would escalate.  Will Iran
कितना एस्केलेट होगा। क्या यहां पर ईरान
attack more bases here?  This did
और ज्यादा बेससेस के ऊपर अटैक करेगा? ऐसा
not happen.  It turns out that Iran attacked only the
हुआ नहीं। पता चलता है कि ईरान ने सिर्फ
Qatari base, the Alaid Al Udeid
कतर वाला जो बेस है ये जो अलैद अल उदैद
Air Base, and that is why,
एयर बेस है वहीं पर हमला किया और इसीलिए
if you see, Trump here
अगर आप देखिए तो यहां पर ट्रंप ने एक तरह
showed it as a victory in a way.  Trump
से इसको विक्ट्री दिखाई। ट्रंप ने यहां पर
posted on social media here and said,
सोशल मीडिया पर पोस्ट किया और कहा कि
look, Iran had fired 14 missiles.
देखिए ईरान ने 14 मिसाइल्स फायर किए थे।
We intercepted and shot down 13 of them
जिसमें से 13 को हमने इंटरसेप्ट करके गिरा
and left the other one
दिया और जो एक था वो हमने छोड़ दिया
because it was non-threatening to us.
क्योंकि वो कोई नॉन थ्रेटनिंग था हमारे
We were not incurring any loss so
लिए। हमें नुकसान नहीं हो रहा था तो इसलिए
we left it.  He went and fell down.  So
हमने उसको छोड़ दिया। वो जाकर गिर गया। सो
I am please to repeat that no Americans
आई एम प्लीज टू रिपीट दैट नो अमेरिकनंस
were harmed.  And he also said that
वेर हार्म। और साथ ही साथ उन्होंने कहा कि
this attack by Iran was very weak.
यह जो अटैक था ईरान का वो बहुत ही कमजोर
And at the same time, Donald Trump was also
था। और साथ ही साथ डोन्ड ट्रंप यह भी
indicating that Iran's entire
इंडिकेट कर रहे थे कि अगर ईरान का पूरा
objective has been destroyed because, look, if
मकसद खत्म हो गया है क्योंकि देखो अगर
America has attacked Iran, then there will be pressure
अमेरिका ने ईरान पर हमला किया है तो ईरान
on the Iranian government and the Iranian establishment to
की सरकार पर ईरान की एस्टैब्लिशमेंट पर भी
take revenge from America.
प्रेशर होगा कि आप अमेरिका से बदला लीजिए।
So Donald Trump was saying in a way
तो डॉनल्ड ट्रंप ये कह रहे थे एक प्रकार
that look, now Iran has given a reply.  The
से कि देखो अब ईरान ने एक जवाब दे दिया
response may have been weak but the
है। जवाब भले ही कमजोर था लेकिन ईरान को
satisfaction that Iran wanted to get was to show its people that
जो सेटिस्फेक्शन मिलना था अपने लोगों को
look, we have also attacked the
दिखाना था कि देखो हमने भी हमला किया है
US base, and that has happened.  And
यूएस के बेसिस के ऊपर तो वो हो गया है। और
that is why if you see,
इसीलिए अगर आप देखोगे तो यहां पर डोन्ड
what is the last line that Donald Trump wrote here, perhaps
ट्रंप ने लास्ट लाइन क्या लिखी परहप्स
Iran can now proceed towards peace and harmony
ईरान कैन नाउ प्रोसीड टू पीस एंड हार्मोनी
in the region and I will enthusiastically
इन द रीजन एंड आई विल एंथूजियास्टिकली
encourage Israel to do the same.  I would like
एनकरेज इजराइल टू डू द सेम। मैं चाहूंगा
Israel to do that too.  Meaning, Donald Trump was, in a way,
कि इजराइल भी वो करे। मतलब एक प्रकार से
calling for a ceasefire
सीज फायर का आह्वान कर रहे थे डोनाल्ड
through this particular post.
ट्रंप इस पर्टिकुलर पोस्ट के माध्यम से।
Now, in the next few moments, within a few hours,
अब अगले ही कुछ पल में कुछ घंटे में जो है
another social media post from Donald Trump
डॉन्ड ट्रंप का एक और यहां पर सोशल मीडिया
comes and in it,
पोस्ट आता है और इसके अंदर यहां पर
he announces about the ceasefire.
उन्होंने अनाउंस कर दिया सीज फायर के बारे
Donald Trump said congratulations
में। डोन्ड ट्रंप ने कहा कांग्रेचुलेशंस
to everyone.  It has been fully agreed by
टू एवरीवन। इट हैज़ बीन फुल्ली एग्रीड बाय
and between Israel and Iran that there will be
एंड बिटवीन इजराइल एंड ईरान दैट देयर विल
a complete and total ceasefire.  And here
बी अ कंप्लीट एंड टोटल सीज फायर। और यहां
basically Donald Trump said that
पर बेसिकली डोनल्ड ट्रंप का ये कहना था कि
Iran will stop its attack in the next 6 hours.
अगले 6 घंटे में जो ईरान है वो अपना अटैक
Israel will stop its attack in the next 12 hours
रोकेगा। अगले 12 घंटे में इजराइल अपना
and ultimately there will be a
अटैक रोकेगा और अल्टीमेटली 24 आवर्स के
complete surrender within 24 hours.  Meaning,
अंदर-अंदर कंप्लीट सीसपायर हो जाएगा। मतलब
this war of 12 days will be officially ended.
यह जो वॉर था 12 दिन का उसको ऑफिशियली एंड
And see, Donald Trump is praising
कर दिया जाएगा। और देखिए डॉन्ड ट्रंप इस
both the countries in this particular post.
पर्टिकुलर पोस्ट में दोनों ही देश को
Congratulating both the countries.  He said,
कांग्रेचुलेट कर रहे हैं। उनका कहना है कि
I would like to congratulate both countries
आई वुड लाइक टू कांग्रेचुलेट बोथ कंट्रीज
Israel and Iran on having the stamina,
इजराइल एंड ईरान ऑन हैविंग द स्टैमिना
courage and intelligence to end what should be called
करेज एंड इंटेलिजेंस टू एंड एंड व्हाट शुड
the 12 Day War.  In fact, Donald
बी कॉल्ड द 12 डे वॉर। इनफैक्ट डोनल्ड
Trump said that this particular
ट्रंप का यह कहना था कि यह जो पर्टिकुलर
war would have lasted for many years and would have
वॉर है यह कई वर्षों तक चलता और मिडिल
completely destroyed the Middle East.  So God
ईस्ट को पूरी तरह से तबाह कर देता। सो गॉड
bless Iran, God bless Israel, God bless the
ब्लेस ईरान, गॉड ब्लेस इजराइल, गॉड ब्लेस
Middle East, God bless the United
दी मिडिल ईस्ट, गॉड ब्लेस द यूनाइटेड
States of America.  And
स्टेट्स ऑफ अमेरिका। और इसी को लेकर
he ended his tweet regarding this.
उन्होंने अपना जो ट्वीट है वो एंड कर
Meaning, Donald Trump has in a way
दिया। मतलब डोनल्ड ट्रंप ने एक तरह से सीज
announced a ceasefire that a
फायर का जो है अनाउंसमेंट कर दिया कि
ceasefire has been imposed between Israel and Iran.
इजराइल और ईरान के बीच में सीज फायर हो
But at the same time
चुका है। लेकिन साथ ही साथ डोनल्ड ट्रंप
another post from Donald Trump came and it was very
का एक और पोस्ट आया था और ये बहुत ही
interesting.  See, what happened was that
इंटरेस्टिंग था। देखिए क्या था ना कि जब
after America bombed Iran, some news started coming in the news
बाद कुछ खबरें आ रही थी न्यूज़ में आ रहा
that Russia can supply nuclear weapons and
था कि रशिया जो है वो न्यूक्लियर वेपंस जो
nuclear bombs to Iran.
है न्यूक्लियर बॉम्ब जो है वह ईरान को
And this thing actually,
सप्लाई कर सकता है। और यह चीज़ एक्चुअली
if you see,
अगर आप देखोगे जो रशिया के फॉर्मर
Medvedev was coming from the side of former President of Russia.
प्रेसिडेंट हैं मेडवडे उनकी तरफ से आ रहा
And Trump took a dig at this.  See
था। और इसी पर चुटकी ली ट्रंप ने। देखिए
what Trump said?  Did I Hear Former
ट्रंप ने क्या कहा? डिड आई हियर फॉर्मर
President Medvedev From Russia Casually
प्रेसिडेंट मेडव फ्रॉम रशिया कैजुअली
Throwing Around the End Word?  We were
थ्रोइंग अराउंड द एंड वर्ड? न्यूक्लियर के
talking about nuclear.  So he said, did he
बारे में बात कर रहे थे। तो उनका कहना था
really say that and is it just a
कि डिड ही रियली से दैट और इज़ इट जस्ट अ
pigment of my imagination?  If he has
पिगमेंट ऑफ़ माय इमेजिनेशन? अगर उन्होंने
said this then let me know immediately.  The
यह चीज बोला है तो लेट मी नो इमीडिएटली। द
N word should not be treated so casually.
एन वर्ड शुड नॉट बी ट्रीटेड सो कैजुअली।
I guess that's why Putin's the boss.  So in a
आई गेस दैट्स व्हाई पुतिनस द बॉस। तो एक
way they were saying that at least the former
प्रकार से कह रहे थे कि ये तो चलो फॉर्मर
President has said it.  But
प्रेसिडेंट ने कह दिया। लेकिन अल्टीमेट
who is the ultimate boss?  It belongs to Putin.  If someone uses the N word
बॉस कौन है? पुतिन का है। अगर कोई एन वर्ड
let me know, I will
का इस्तेमाल करता है तो लेट मी नो मैं
tell you.  And look here, what Donald Trump
बताता हूं। और देखिए यहां पर डॉनल्ड ट्रंप
said, that what we have is
का क्या कहना था कि हमारे पास जो चीज है
20 years ahead of time.  And
ना वो 20 साल आगे एडवांस की चीजें हैं। और
if we attack with it, nothing will survive.
अगर हमने उससे हमला किया तो कुछ भी बच
So in addition to our great
नहीं पाएगा। सो इन एडिशन टू आवर ग्रेट
fighter pilots, thank you to the captain and
फाइटर पायलट्स थैंक यू टू द कैप्टन एंड
crew.  So here he was also
क्रू। तो यहां पर वो इस न्यूक्लियर को भी
taking a dig at Donald Trump regarding nuclear weapons, saying do
लेकर चुटकी ले रहे थे डोन्ड ट्रंप कि हमें
n't tell us what nuclear weapons are?
मत बताओ कि न्यूक्लियर होता क्या है?
Because we are the boss means we know
क्योंकि हम बॉस हैं उसके मतलब हम जानते
what kind of technology we have.
हैं कि हमारे पास किस तरह की टेक्नोलॉजी
Well, the question here now is,
है। खैर यहां पर अब क्वेश्चन ये आता है कि
what did Iran have to say after Donald Trump claimed ceasefire?
किया उसके बाद ईरान का क्या कहना था? ईरान
If you look from Iran's side, their foreign
की तरफ से अगर आप देखोगे उनके जो फॉरेन
minister, Syed Abbas Araqchi,
मिनिस्टर हैं सैयद अब्बास अर अरकची
said that Iran has repeatedly made it
उन्होंने कहा एज ईरान हैज़ रिपीटेडली मेड
clear that Israel has launched war against Iran.
क्लियर कि इजराइल ने वॉर ल्च किया है ईरान
We have not started a war here.
के ऊपर। हमने यहां पर वॉर ल्च नहीं किया
So first of all the one who should stop the
है। तो पहले यहां पर जिसको रोकना चाहिए
war here should be Israel because in
वॉर को वो इजराइल को रोकना चाहिए क्योंकि
a way it was Israel who started this war.
इजराइल ने ही ये वॉर को एक तरह से स्टार्ट
So as of now there is no
किया था। सो एज ऑफ नाउ देयर इज़ नो
agreement.  So, in a way, Trump's
एग्रीमेंट। तो एक प्रकार से जो ट्रंप का
claim regarding ceasefire was completely rejected by Iran's
क्लेम था सीज़ फायर का उसको ईरान के ईरान
Foreign Minister saying that there is
के जो फॉरेन मिनिस्टर हैं उन्होंने
no
कंप्लीटली रिजेक्ट कर दिया दैट देयर इज़ नो
agreement on any ceasefire or cessation of
एग्रीमेंट ऑन एनी सीज़ फायर और ससेशन ऑफ
military operations.  However he said that
मिलिट्री ऑपरेशन। हाउएवर उन्होंने कहा कि
if Israel stops things here then
अगर इजराइल यहां पर चीजों को रोकता है तब
we will think further whether to impose ceasefire or
हम आगे सोचेंगे कि क्या सीज फायर करना है
not.  This was said by Syed Abbas Arachi
कि नहीं। ये सैयद अब्बास अराची का कहना था
and just after that you
और उसके जस्ट कुछ ही देर बाद ये आप देख
can see that this tweet came at 6:16.
सकते हो यह जो ट्वीट है वो आया था 6:16।
Ok?  This morning then after half an hour,
ठीक है? आज सुबह फिर उसके आधे घंटे बाद
what does one mean after 15-20 minutes,
आधे घंटे क्या मतलब 15 20 मिनट के बाद ही
another tweet comes in which perhaps it is
एक और ट्वीट आता है जिसके अंदर शायद ऐसा
indicated that yes, Iran also
इंडिकेट किया जाता है कि हां ईरान भी सीज
wants to ceasefire, and look, he said the
फायर करना चाहता है और देखिए उन्होंने कहा
military operations of our powerful armed
मिलिट्री ऑपरेशंस ऑफ आवर पावरफुल आर्म्ड
forces to punish Israel should end now, which
फोर्सेस टू पनिश इजराइल ये अब खत्म हो
means by 4:00 PM we have completed it, together with
मतलब 4:00 बजे तक हमने इसको पूरा किया है
all Iranians, I thank our brave
टुगेदर विथ ऑल इरानियंस आई थैंक आवर ब्रेव
armed forces, meaning in a way he was being
आर्म्ड सोर्सेस मतलब एक तरह से वो थ
thankful, was thanking his
थैंकफुल हो रहे थे थैंक्यू दे रहे थे अपने
armed forces, so somewhere a
आर्म्ड फोर्सेस को लेकर तो कहीं ना कहीं
person does that only when things are coming to an end.
इंसान वो तभी करता है जब चीजें चीजें एंड
So this indication was
हो रही होती हैं। तो यहां पर ये इंडिकेशन
coming here.  Look, even now Israel has
आ रहा था। देखिए अभी भी इजराइल ने ये
not announced this because
अनाउंस नहीं किया क्योंकि उसके जस्ट बाद
if you look just after that, even before that, the
अगर आप देखो जस्ट बाद क्या उसके पहले ही
supreme leader of Iran had
यहां पर जो ईरान के सुप्रीम लीडर हैं
announced that we will
उन्होंने अनाउंस कर दिया था कि हम सरेंडर
not surrender.  Iran's Supreme Leader
नहीं करेंगे। ईरान के सुप्रीम लीडर का
said those who know the Iranian people and
कहना था दोज़ हु नो द ईरानियन पीपल एंड
their history know that the Iranian nation is
देयर हिस्ट्री नो दैट द ईरानियन नेशन इज
not a nation that will surrender.  We
नॉट अ नेशन दैट सरेंडर। हम सरेंडर करने
are not among those who surrender.  So that is why there
वालों में से नहीं है। तो इसीलिए एक
is an atmosphere of confusion as to whether Iran has
प्रकार का कंफ्यूजन का माहौल है कि ईरान
actually accepted the ceasefire or not.
ने एक्चुअल में सीज फायर माना है कि नहीं।
Because let me tell you,
क्योंकि मैं आपको बता दूं सीज फायर अनाउंस
just a short while ago after the ceasefire was announced, the news
होने के बाद अभी जस्ट कुछ ही देर पहले खबर
came that an Iranian missile that was inside Israel has
आती है कि इजराइल के अंदर जो मिसाइल है वो
hit it.  If you look at this,
हिट किया है ईरान का। ये अगर आप देखोगे
in Southern Israel, this is called the Gaza Strip,
सदर्न इजराइल में ये गाज़ा स्ट्रिप हो गया
and just on its eastern side, there is a
और इसके जस्ट ईस्टर्न साइड में यहां पर एक
city, a place called Beshba, and it is being reported there that
शहर है एक जगह है बेशबा और वहां पर बताया
at least three people have lost their lives due to a missile hitting a residential apartment.
मिसाइल हिट करने की वजह से कम से कम तीन
Three Israelis were
लोगों की जाने गई हैं। तीन इजराइलियों की
killed.  So should ceasefire be
जाने गई हैं। तो क्या यहां पर सीज फायर
considered here?  It should not be believed because the missile
माना जाए? नहीं माना जाए क्योंकि मिसाइल
attack has started again.  Overall
अटैक तो फिर से स्टार्ट हो गया है। ओवरऑल
look at the bigger picture here?  What was each one
देखिए बिगर पिक्चर क्या है यहां पर? हर एक
's goal?  What was Iran's goal?   We had to
का गोल क्या था? ईरान का गोल क्या था?
show Iran that we are not collapsing internally.
ईरान को दिखाना था कि हम इंटरनली कोलैप्स
He wanted to show his strength
नहीं हो रहे हैं। वो अपने ताकत को दिखाना
that
चाहता था कि वेस्टर्न जो हेजमनी है जो
we will stand firmly against the hegemony that the western countries want
वेस्टर्न कंट्रीज चाहती हैं हम उसके सामने
and
डट कर खड़े खड़े रहेंगे एंड यहां पर
will survive here without any compromise.
सर्वाइव करेंगे विदाउट एनी कॉम्प्रोमाइज।
Meaning, you can impose any sensation or do anything to us.
मतलब चाहे सेंशंस लगा दो, कुछ कर दो हमारे
So, somewhere Iran was also trying to show that
ऊपर। तो कहीं ना कहीं ईरान भी वो दिखाना
and to a large extent, if you observe,
चाह रहा था और काफी हद तक अगर आप देखोगे
Iran has also shown that no matter how much you
तो ईरान ने दिखाया भी है कि आप कितना भी
attack, we are still
हमला कर दो हम फिर भी आपके ऊपर अटैक करने
ready to attack you.  What was Israel's goal on the other side
के लिए रेडी हैं। दूसरी तरफ इजराइल का गोल
?  Israel was repeatedly saying that we do
क्या था? इजराइल बार-बार कह रहा था कि हम
not want Iran to be
नहीं चाहते कि ईरान की न्यूक्लियर
deprived of nuclear capability.  This means that even in the future
कैपेबिलिटी ना मिले। मतलब आगे फ्यूचर में
Iran will not be able to attack us.
भी ईरान जो है हमारे ऊपर अटैक ना कर सके।
Now has this goal been completely achieved?   There's
अब क्या ये पूरी तरह से गोल अचीव हुआ है?
a big question over this.  Because
इसके ऊपर एक बड़ा प्रश्न है। क्योंकि
this was America's goal as well.  Trump's
अमेरिका का भी तो गोल यही था। ट्रंप का
goal again was that he wanted to show
गोल अगेन ये था कि वो दिखाना चाह रहे थे
that look, I am very powerful here.  When
कि देखो मैं यहां पर काफी पावरफुल हूं। जब
I come to war things are over.
मैं वॉर में आता हूं तो चीजें खत्म हो
So, in a way, he also
जाती हैं। तो एक प्रकार से वो भी दिखाना
wants to show that.  But the question is
चाह रहे हैं। लेकिन क्वेश्चन ये है कि
whether the
क्या एक्चुअल में ईरान के पास जो
nuclear capability that Iran actually had and the things it was doing have been
न्यूक्लियर कैपेबिलिटी थी जो चीजें वो कर
completely destroyed.  Look,
रहा था वो पूरी तरह से खत्म हुई। देखो अभी
we cannot say this 100% right now because yesterday there were
100% हम नहीं कह सकते क्योंकि कल कुछ
reports that 400 kg of 60%
खबरें भी आ रही थी कि 400 किलो ऑफ जो 60%
enriched uranium had already been
एनरच्ड यूरेनियम है वो ईरान ने पहले ही
removed by Iran from the For Two site.  So if this
फॉर दो साइट से हटा दिया था। तो अगर ऐसा
is the case then after some time there was a slight delay.
है तो फिर कुछ ही टाइम बाद थोड़ा सा डिले
But after some time Iran will
हो गया। लेकिन कुछ ही टाइम बाद ईरान के
regain that capability.  So it will be
पास वो कैपेबिलिटी फिर आ जाएगी। तो वो
interesting to see here whether
देखने वाली बात होगी यहां पर कि क्या
Israel and America have been able to achieve that goal
इजराइल और अमेरिका ने वो गर्ल अचीव कर पाए
or not.  So let's see what happens.
हैं कि नहीं। तो लेट्स सी क्या होता है।
But what do you think about the whole matter
बट बाकी आपका क्या सोचना है इन सारे मामले
?  Please let me know in the comments.
को लेकर? मुझे कमेंट्स में जरूर बताइएगा।
And before I go, I have a very interesting
और जाने से पहले एक बहुत ही इंटरेस्टिंग
question.  The question here is,
क्वेश्चन है। क्वेश्चन यहां पर ये है कि
which countries are included in India's Strategic Energy Reserve Partnership Agreement?  Which of these
उसमें कौन-कौन से देश हैं? इनमें से कौन
countries are part of India's SPR Partnership
से देश भारत के एसपीआर पार्टनरशिप
Agreement?  You all know its right answer.  You
एग्रीमेंट का पार्ट हैं? इसका राइट आंसर
will find it on my Instagram.  It doesn't matter if you are not there.  You
मिलेगा ही। वहां पर अगर आप नहीं हो कोई
can get its
बात नहीं। Telegram से ले सकते हैं इसका
correct answer from Telegram.  And friends, our
सही उत्तर। और दोस्तों हमारा जो 2026 का
foundation batch of 2026 is the
फाउंडेशन बैच है यूपीएससी 2026 का
Pratigya batch of UPSC 2026 in which complete preparation is
प्रतिज्ञा बैच जिसमें कंप्लीट प्रिपरेशन
done for prelims, mains, interview and
कराई जाती है प्रीलिम्स मेंस इंटरव्यू और
if you crack the prelims, then the
अगर आपका प्रीलिम्स क्रैक भी हो जाता है
entire fee will also be refunded to you.
तो पूरा का पूरा फीस भी आपको रिफंड कर
If you still have any doubt
दिया जाएगा। अगर आपको अभी भी कोई डाउट हो
regarding the batch then you can call my personal team.
बैच को लेकर तो आप मेरी पर्सनल ये जो टीम
This exact
है उसको कॉल कर सकते हैं। ये एग्जैक्ट
number is given.  If you call here,
नंबर दिया हुआ है। यहां पर अगर आप कॉल
you will get to know all the doubts related to the batch.
रिलेटेड वो आपको पता चल जाएंगे। इसके
Whatever features you want to know in detail,
जितने भी फीचर्स आप जानना चाहो डिटेल में
you can ask about them over the phone.  And definitely
वो आप फोन पर पूछ सकते हैं। एंड डेफिनेटली
use this code Ankit Live so that you
यूज़ करिएगा यह कोड अंकित लाइव ताकि आप
can avail maximum discount on our batches.  So I hope you liked this video.  I will
ले सकें। सो आई होप कि ये वीडियो आपको
meet you next time then
पसंद आया होगा। मिलता हूं आपसे नेक्स्ट
thank you very much.
एंटिल देन थैंक यू वेरी मच।